Chris: Software developers need to use
good coding principles and practices.
Good coding practices are important in programming
and are achieved by using a variety of principles,
which may initially seem tedious and time
consuming but may be advantageous long term.
Leah: Cluttered code can cause problems when it is
further extended, and when the same code needs to be
worked on by a wider ‘Developer team’, so this is one of
the reasons why there are rules for writing good code.
Let’s take a look at some of the most common principles
used in programming and software development:
Chris: The KISS Principle
The KISS Principle is a term that is widely used
in a variety of different industries so let’s look
at what it means especially in relation to coding.
KISS is an acronym for a design principle noted by
the US Navy in 1960 and it stands for ‘Keep it Simple
and Straightforward’ and covers many different areas
of design including engineering and programming.
There are other variations of this including ‘keep
it short and simple’ and ‘keep it simple, stupid’.
Whatever way it is used it means the same thing.
Leah: ‘Keep it simple stupid’ or even ‘keep it
short simple’ are most commonly used in programming.
By keeping the programming simple, service and
maintenance are much easier and there are no hard and
fast rules regarding the implementation of code, only
that it should be simple and therefore easily modified.
There are a number of ways to keep
your code simple these could include:
Chris: variables – keep the scope as small as
possible, don’t reuse variables, declare the
variables you are using and name them properly.
Functions – keep as small as possible and ‘pure’
DRY – write ‘Don’t Repeat Yourself’ code
YAGNI – Use the ‘You Aren’t Gonna Need It’ principle – in
other words write the least amount of code that you need
SOLID – use the SOLID principle.
Leah: There are many reasons for
implementing the KISS philosophy.
It may prevent you from wasting time and effort developing
complicated protocols which take a long time to write.
However, the primary benefits, are for
those that may use the software afterwards.
This could include both other programmers and
customers who want a product which is simple to use.
Chris: SOLID principles
In programming S O L I D is a mnemonic acronym used for the
five design principles which are intended to make programs
more ‘understandable’, ‘flexible’ and ‘maintainable’.
Let’s look at what these are.
Leah: S - The Single Responsibility Principle
The Single Responsibility Principle [SRP] states
that every class or method is responsible for one
single, separate part of a program’s functionality.
In other words each class should
only have one reason to change.
Good practice of SRP will prevent side-effects from
future changes and make software easier to implement.
Chris: O – Open / Closed Principle
Software entities should be open for
extension but closed for modification.
In other words you should be able to add new
functionality without changing the existing code.
So, for example with OCP, if you change one class
there is no need to change all related classes.
Leah: L – Liskov Substitution Principle
Properties of one original class should be
replaceable with objects built from classes adapted
from the original without breaking the application.
For example, if you had a ‘superclass’ with its own
‘subclasses’, with LSP you can change the objects of the
‘subclass’ without affecting its associated ‘superclass’.
Chris: I – Interface Segregation Principle
No client should be forced to
depend on methods they do not use.
With ISP it is good practice to have several client specific
interfaces rather than one large general-purpose interface.
This reduces the side effects that could occur from
using a larger interface as the developers would
be focused on their own client specific interface.
Leah: D – Dependency Inversion Principle
Abstraction should be used to decouple
high-level and low-level modules from each other.
This way high-level modules which sustain
complex systems, are not affected by low-level
modules which provide utility features.
High and low level modules should depend on
abstractions which do not depend on details.
This means that if the details change,
they do not affect the abstraction.
Abstraction is one of the key principles of
object-oriented programming where the programmer
hides all but the relevant data about an object
to reduce its complexity and increase efficiency.